Impact Visuals Photograph Collection
Impact Visuals Photograph Collection
1984-2000
Impact Visuals
0.25 linear ft.
Photographs documenting protests relating to labor, trade, health care, jobs, etc., mostly in the United States but a few in Canada, Guatemala, and India
5900296
Biographical History
Impact Visuals (1986-2001) was a New York City-based photo agency, archive, and publication service, with a focus on social justice, equity, and multicultural issues. Founded by Michael Kaufman, the co-op provided photographs and photojournalist services to a variety of clients, from mainstream newspapers and magazines to progressive, non-profit organizations and alternative media. At some point, Impact Visuals acquired the archive of South African cooperative Afrapix which was added to their archive. Impact "[had] a core value of documenting people and their fight for self-determination. Also the goal is to support the photographers who do this kind of work and are members of the co-op." ["Nicholas Herman interviews Katie Brennan", The Co-operative Learning Centre, undated]
Impact was cooperatively owned, with a high bar for membership; its 80 or so member photographers received 50% of the revenue generated from their archive sales and 60% of their assignment sales, but retained copyright to their images and were allowed to market their work independently. Members were expected to be "photographically skilled with a consistently unique style of shooting, someone that is dedicated to political and social awareness, someone that is able to produce at a consistently high level, and someone who will add to the racial, ethnic, sexual and geographical diversity of the cooperative. Of utmost importance is the applicants independence, motivation and interest in working together towards a common goal." [Geraldine Baum, "Impact Visuals Internship Journal", Spring 1996]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Impact Visuals Photograph Collection contains black-and-white photographs taken by members of the New York City photographers' co-operative. Reflecting Impact Visuals' focus on documenting social justice issues, most are of protests, rallies, marches, and other expressions of public pressure for change.
Subjects include budget cuts, the Republican legislative agenda known as "Contract with America", health care, jobs/unemployment, "living wage," and the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA). Most of the photographs are of events in the United States, but there are a few from Canada, India, and Guatemala. Specific issues, organizations, and identified individuals are given in the inventory below. An index to photographers whose work appears in the collection may be found at the end of this finding aid.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by topic; the few international photos are filed at the end.
Related Material
Impact Visuals' archive is held by the Thomas J. Dodd Center at the University of Connecticut.
Subject and Genre Headings
Activism and social reform; Photography; Radicalism; Jackson, Jesse.; Wallis, Jim.; Impact Visuals.; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.; Sojourners Fellowship.; Documentary photography -- United States.; United States -- Economic policy.; Environmentalism -- United States.; North American Free Trade Agreement (1992 December 17); Protest movements -- United States.; Strikes and lockouts -- United States.; Trade regulation -- United States.; Photographs.; Photographers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advance notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 2020.
Inventory
- Photographs
  - Banking and finance, 1991; 1993-1995; interest rates, mortgage rates, etc. (Box 1)
    9 Jan 1991, Washington, DC - FDIC chairman William Seidman, Comptroller Robert Clarke at Senate Banking Committee hearing on bankruptcy of Bank of New England
    11 Sep 1991, Washington, DC - Clark Clifford and Robert Altman at House hearings on BCCI and First American Bank
    Apr 1993, Brooklyn - couple meeting with lawyer to refinance mortgage
    15 Nov 1994, Washington, DC - rally in front of Federal Reserve during meeting of Federal Open Market Committee
    9 Oct 1995, Washington, DC - "BAP! the Bank" March and Rally, sponsored by Fifty Years is Enough
  - Budget cuts, 1991-1992; 1995 (Box 1)
    4 Feb 1991, Brooklyn - demonstrators in front of Brooklyn Public Library
    30 Apr 1991, New York City - union workers and others, on Wall Street and near World Trade Center
    14 Mar 1992, Washington, DC - union workers (AFGE/AFSCME) protesting in Mayor Sharon Pratt Kelly's neighborhood
    27 Mar 1995, Albany, NY - civil service workers protesting at state capitol; Mental Health Action Network
    6 May 1995, New York City - protests in Times Square
  - "Contract with America", 1995 (Box 1)
    29 Mar 1995, Ann Arbor, MI - students and welfare rights workers, University of Michigan
    4 Apr 1995, Detroit, MI - NAACP, SEIU, other organizations
    14 Aug 1995, Yorba Linda, CA - Teamsters and others protesting Gingrich's book signing ceremony at the Nixon Library
    18 Aug 1995, Boston, MA - environmental, labor, pro-choice, and LGBT groups protesting Gingrich's book signing at Lauriat's Bookstore
  - Health care, 1990 (Box 1)
    13 Jun 1990, Albany NY - union members and others at state capitol
    3 Oct 1990, New York City - municipal workers at City Hall Park
  - Jobs, 1984; 1987,; 1989,; 1991-1993; including layoffs, plant closings, unemployment (Box 1)
    1984, Paterson NJ - member of Typographical Union who lost job due to automation
    Mar 1987, Detroit, MI - UAW workers protesting plant closings; lines of workers at unemployment office
    Nov 1989, Detroit, MI - UAW workers protesting plant closings
    Aug 1991, Rochester, NH - applicants waiting in line for hours to apply for jobs at Cabletron
    Feb 1992, Manchester, NH - volunteers and unemployed at New Horizons Soup Kitchen
    14 Jul 1992, New York City - "March of the Unemployed" outside Madison Square Garden during Democratic National Convention
    29 Jul 1992, Detroit, MI - protests against privatization of emergency medical services (EMS)
    18 Feb 1993, Washington, DC - unemployed workers from Pennsylvania protesting for extension of benefits
    6 Apr 1993, Chicago, IL - applicants waiting in line for hours to apply for jobs at Michael Jordan's new restaurant
    14 Apr 1993, Rochester, NY - Movement for a People's Assembly outside Kodak plant as part of "National Job is a Right Campaign"
    21 Jun 1993, Fresno, CA - applicants waiting in line for hours to apply for jobs at Walmart
    Oct 1993, New York City - anti-layoff demonstration of hospital workers
    11 Nov 1993, Detroit, MI - applicants waiting in line for hours to apply for future jobs at potential new casino
  - Living wage, 1996; 1998 (Box 1)
    24 Aug 1996, Chicago, IL - members of ACORN, SEIU, and others at Navy Pier during Democratic National Convention
    7 Sep 1998, Alexandria, VA - Labor Day rally, mostly Latino workers, sponsored by Northern Virginia Livable Wage Campaign and Tenants and Workers Support Committee
  - NAFTA, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    1992, New York City - General Motors layoffs
    8 Jan 1993, Austin, TX - protesters outside during meeting between President Bill Clinton and Mexican President Salinas de Gortari
    1 May 1993, Seattle, WA - "Not this NAFTA" rally organized by NAFTA/GATT Justice Committee and the Washington Coalition for Fair Trade and Social Justice
    5 May 1993, Cleveland, OH - UAW members and others at rally organized by Jobs with Justice and a coalition of local activists
    8 May 1993, Northfield, MN - protest at Armory, spurred by local firm Sheldahl Co. moving operations to Mexico
    18 Sep 1993, Marcus Hook, PA - rally of unions, environmental activists, peace groups, and Mexican mushroom farm workers
    2 Oct 1993, Buffalo, NY - Jesse Jackson with local labor and political leaders at Trico plant
    23 Oct 1993, Atlanta, GA - union workers and environmental activists at state capitol
    Nov 1993, Queens, NY - Queens Coalition to Stop NAFTA, Rego Park
    10 Nov 1993, New York City - ILGWU members in garment district
    12 Nov 1993, Tucson, AZ - homeless and others protesting outside Representative Jim Kolbe's office
  - Miscellaneous, identified, 1988-1995; 2000 (Box 1)
    Sep 1988, New York City - Labor Day parade, signs expressing solidarity with Mexican workers
    21 Oct 1989, St. Louis, MO - Victor Reuther at UAW New Directions Movement First National Congress
    7 Oct 1990, New York City - tourists being turned away from the Statue of Liberty, closed due to government shutdown
    [Jan?] 1991, Dover, DE - migrant farm worker
    15 May 1992, Washington, DC - "Save Our Cities" march/rally; signs include mention of Rodney King and police brutality
    3 Jun 1994, Cincinnati, OH - SEIU District 925 President Debbie Schneider and Mayor Diane Qualls at union's annual meeting
    1 Dec 1994, Washington, DC - protesters against GATT outside White House
    6 Dec 1995, Washington, DC - Sojourners members (including Jim Wallis, Tony Campolo, and Eugene Rivers) protesting GOP budget as anti-poor people, at US Capitol Building
    18 Jun 2000, Eugene, OR - police in riot gear clearing protesters
  - Miscellaneous, unidentified, includes CWA workers on strike against AT&T (Box 1)
  - International, Canada (Box 1)
    26 Aug 1991, Toronto, ONT - Canadian Union of Postal Workers protesting privatization outside sorting plant of Canada Post
    28 Apr 1993, Windsor, ONT - Workers Memorial Day march
    24 Nov 1993, Toronto, ONT - Ontario Public Service Employees Union at Queen's Park (provincial legislature), protesting "social contract"
    11 Dec 1995, London, ONT - postal workers outside sorting plant of Canada Post, protesting anti-labor policies and cutbacks of Ontario premier Mike Harris
  - International, Guatemala (Box 1)
    3 Feb 1997, Mixco - protesters against unfair tax burden; foreground is close-up of young police officer's face
  - International, India (Box 1)
    2 Feb 1987, New Delhi - sit-in by nurses outside residence of Human Resource Minister
    1 Dec 1994, New Delhi - child labor at evening wedding
Index to photographers
This index includes all photographers whose work is represented in the collection, with the topic folders where their work may be found.
Anderson, MarilynJobs NAFTA
Beiler, RyanGuatemala
Binder, DonnaNAFTA
Burke, BillJobs
Chase, FredNAFTA
Cohen, GeorgeHealth care
Condyles, J. KirkBudget cuts NAFTA Misc/identified
Curtis, RodneyJobs
Dimitrov, SlobodanContract with America
Dotter, EarlJobs
Eliason, OrdeIndia
Finkle, HarveyNAFTA
Fox, RobertMisc/identified
Friar, JeromeBanking Budget cuts Misc/identified
Frumhoff, MartiMisc/identified
Garg, ArvindIndia
Hartman, DavidCanada
Horn, AnsellBanking/finance
Humphries, MarilynContract with America
Jensen, KurtMisc/identified
Kumar, AmitavaNAFTA
Latimer, SteveJobs
Lichtenstein, AndrewBudget cuts
Ludak, MarkJobs
Marcus, HilaryMisc/identified
Marshall, RussJobs
McKitterick, TomBudget cuts
Neipris, EllenBudget cuts Health care
Palmer, BrianJobs
PoKempner, MarcLiving wage
Reinhard, RickBanking/finance Living wage Misc/identified
Santow, LorenJobs
Savino, TonyMisc/identified
Schuerholz, DanaNAFTA
Scott, JeffryNAFTA
Smith, CatherineHealth care
Smith, ChristopherBudget cuts
Sorrentino, JosephMisc/identified
Stone, LesMisc/identified
Swift, ThorJobs
Tabor, MarthaBanking/finance
Taylor, AdamNAFTA
Tynan, JimJobs
van Lier, PietNAFTA
West, JimContract with America Jobs Canada